Valentina Kononova

Data Scientist

Master of Science with 2 years of international experience in natural language processing. Designed and deployed a variety of models using advanced AI/ML algorithms. Looking for a team to continue professional growth and add more value

EXPERIENCE

Reputation Earth, Kazan - Data Scientist

June 2019 - present

- Built and optimized binary and multi-label models for sentiment and topic classification with accuracy up to 91%
- Conducted researches on natural language processing tasks: text segmentation, named entities recognition, phrases extraction, clustering and classification
- Scraped, parsed and prepared (text segmentation, cleaning and labelling) data for training machine learning models
- Deployed production models to generate responses based on sentiment and semantic of customer's reviews

Siemens, Kazan and Ilmenau - Scholar

September 2016 - August 2018

- Conducted researches on sensor data validation using ML algorithms (time series classification, clustering, visualization)
- Wrote and defended a master thesis on Sensor Data Validation under the company supervision

State Institute of Applied Optics, Kazan – Engineer

March 2016 - September 2017

- Designed documentation (circuit diagram, Bill-Of-Materials)
- Provided quality assurance of printed circuit boards and their components
- Wrote and defended bachelor thesis on PCB components placement under the company supervision

EDUCATION

TU Ilmenau, Ilmenau — Master of Science in Research in Computer & Systems Engineering 2016 – 2018

Kazan National Research Technical University – KAI, Kazan – *Master of Science in Research in Computer & Systems Engineering* 2016 – 2018

Kazan National Research Technical University – KAI, Kazan – *Bachelor in Computer Science* 2013 – 2016 Kazan, Russia Tel: +7 927 4111 227

E-mail: vkononova.ds@gmail.com

Github: novamind

Linkedin: <u>valentina-kononova</u>
Blog: <u>https://novamind.github.io/</u>

SKILLS & TOOLS

Natural language processing, Machine Learning, Neural Networks, Probability & Statistics

Python, SQL, Jupyter Notebook, VS Code, Docker

Teamwork: Agile, Kanban, Asana, Slack, Git

Python packages: numpy, pandas, spacy, nltk, sklearn, tensorflow, keras

CURRENT PROJECTS & RESEARCHES

Text segmentation into meaningful verb phrases

Multi-label classification research Model training on very imbalanced data

LANGUAGES

Russian Native Speaker
English Upper-Intermediate
German Beginner

INTERESTS

Personal Development
Data science blogging
Volunteer work to protect the
environment
Moderate and participate in a book
club